<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Tales Mançano</title>
<link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Tales Mançano Academic Website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.24</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Hall, P. A. (2003). Aligning Ontology and Methodology in Comparative Research.</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-12-Hall1989/Hall1989.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Hall, P. A. (2003). Aligning Ontology and Methodology in Comparative Research. In J. Mahoney &amp; D. Rueschemeyer (Eds.), Comparative Historical Analysis in the Social Sciences (1st ed., pp.&nbsp;373–404). Cambridge University Press. https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511803963.012</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="gemini-at-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-at-google-drive"><em>Gemini at Google Drive</em></h3>
<p><strong>Sumário do Ensaio: Alinhando Ontologia e Metodologia em Pesquisa Comparativa</strong></p>
<p>O ensaio de Peter A. Hall trata do desalinhamento entre as ontologias (pressupostos sobre a natureza das relações causais no mundo social e político) e as metodologias (meios para aumentar a confiança nas inferências, ou como gosto de dizer, teoria sobre epistemologia, teoria sobre como conhecer o mundo) predominantes na política comparada.</p>
<p><strong>Convergência Histórica de Ontologia e Metodologia:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Institucionalismo Inicial:</strong> A abordagem era descritiva e idiográfica, focada nas instituições formais, com uma ontologia circumscrita que via as instituições como produtos de histórias nacionais.</li>
<li><strong>A Revolução Comparativa (Anos 50 e 60):</strong> Houve uma mudança para a concepção do mundo político como um campo regido por regularidades causais nomológicas (leis válidas no espaço e tempo). Isso impulsionou a busca por generalizações e o desenvolvimento de taxonomias e tipologias, sendo o funcionalismo uma perspectiva causal popular.</li>
<li><strong>O Método Comparativo (Anos 60 e 70):</strong> Com a queda do funcionalismo, a ontologia mudou para imagens orientadas para variáveis, e a busca por regularidades causais passou a ser vista em termos de Mill (métodos de concordância e diferença). Lijphart definiu o método comparativo como essencialmente correlacional, análogo ao método estatístico, mas com um pequeno número de casos (pequeno-N).</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>O Dilema Contemporâneo:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>As metodologias populares (regressão padrão e método comparativo convencional) exigem fortes pressupostos ontológicos, como homogeneidade de unidade e ausência de correlação sistemática com variáveis omitidas.</li>
<li>As novas ontologias da política comparada, como as baseadas em <strong>interação estratégica</strong> e <strong>dependência de trajetória (path dependence)</strong>, violam esses pressupostos, reconhecendo a ubiquidade de:
<ul>
<li>Causação conjuntural múltipla.</li>
<li>Efeitos de interação complexos.</li>
<li>A importância da sequência e do tempo.</li>
<li>Causação recíproca.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Solução Proposta: Análise Sistemática de Processos (Systematic Process Analysis):</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>O método proposto envolve a comparação de previsões de teorias causais, não apenas sobre resultados (variável dependente) e variáveis causais (independentes), mas também sobre o <strong>processo causal</strong> em si (eventos, sequência de eventos, motivações dos atores, etc.).</li>
<li>O estudo de caso único e a pesquisa pequeno-N, quando combinados com a Análise Sistemática de Processos, tornam-se ferramentas poderosas para testar teorias, especialmente as complexas que postulam estruturas causais incompatíveis com os pressupostos da análise de regressão.</li>
<li>O objetivo final é garantir que a escolha do método seja congruente com os pressupostos ontológicos sobre as estruturas causais do mundo.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5"><em>Perplexity with Claude Sonet 4.5</em></h3>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Methodology</category>
  <category>Epistemology</category>
  <category>Ontology</category>
  <category>Comparative Politics</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-12-Hall1989/Hall1989.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Notes for Carnoy 1984</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy1984/Carnoy1984.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Aqui está um resumo abrangente e estruturado do texto fornecido:</p>
<p>O livro, <em>The State and Political Theory</em>, de Martin Carnoy, visa analisar o conceito de Estado a partir de uma perspectiva de classe. O crescimento do setor público, ou Estado, tornou-se uma questão crucial nas sociedades de hoje, pois ele detém a chave para o desenvolvimento econômico, a segurança social e a liberdade individual.</p>
<p><strong>Principais Propósitos do Livro:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Chamar a atenção para o Estado como objeto de investigação.</li>
<li>Demonstrar que as discussões sobre o Estado refletem diferentes visões da sociedade e do papel do Estado.</li>
<li>Mostrar que visões distintas do Estado implicam diferentes políticas de mudança social.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Estrutura da Análise de Teorias do Estado:</strong> O livro compara a visão dominante americana, centrada no pluralismo e corporativismo, com as teorias marxistas.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Teorias do “Bem Comum” (Clássicas e Liberais):</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Clássica (Hobbes, Locke, Rousseau):</strong> Substituiu o direito divino pelos direitos individuais, baseando a autoridade na razão humana e no “bem comum”.</li>
<li><strong>Liberal (Adam Smith, Utilitaristas):</strong> Smith argumentou que o interesse individual (ganho material) maximiza o bem-estar coletivo. Utilitaristas como Bentham e James Mill viam o Estado como necessário para proteger a propriedade e garantir a segurança, mas não para produzir subsistência ou abundância.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Pluralismo:</strong>
<ul>
<li>Modelo empírico em que o Estado é um árbitro neutro.</li>
<li>Schumpeter e os pluralistas veem a democracia como um mecanismo de mercado para escolher líderes (políticos), não como um meio para alcançar o “bem comum”.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Marxistas (Pós-Leninistas):</strong> O livro discute cinco contribuições principais, que veem o Estado a partir de uma perspectiva de classe.
<ul>
<li><strong>Gramsci:</strong> O Estado é um aparelho ideológico que ajuda a legitimar a hegemonia da classe capitalista.</li>
<li><strong>Estruturalismo (Althusser e Poulantzas):</strong> A forma e função do Estado capitalista são determinadas pelas relações de classe e o Estado é “relativamente autônomo”.</li>
<li><strong>Derivacionista (Joachim Hirsch):</strong> A função do Estado é deduzida do processo de acumulação de capital.</li>
<li><strong>Política (Claus Offe):</strong> O Estado é independente do controle capitalista, mas representa seus interesses e é o local principal das crises.</li>
<li><strong>Luta de Classes (Pietro Ingrao e Poulantzas posterior):</strong> O Estado em si é uma arena de conflito de classes, moldado e disputado pelas relações de classe.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p>As tendências recentes na teoria marxista apontam para o Estado como o foco principal da luta de classes e para uma estratégia de transição para o socialismo que é fundamentalmente democrática.</p>
<p>Especificamente o Capítulo 7 sobre teoria da dependência:</p>
<p>O Capítulo 7 do livro, intitulado <strong>“O Estado Dependente”</strong>, discute a natureza e as características do Estado nas sociedades capitalistas menos industrializadas, frequentemente referidas como Terceiro Mundo.</p>
<p>O capítulo explora se o Estado nestes países é um resquício de formas políticas antigas, uma fase temporária do capitalismo, ou se é fundamentalmente diferente devido à sua industrialização tardia e à sua relação histórica com as economias já industrializadas.</p>
<p>Os principais pontos abordados são:</p>
<section id="antecedentes-históricos-e-teóricos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="antecedentes-históricos-e-teóricos">1. Antecedentes Históricos e Teóricos</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Visão Marxista:</strong> O capítulo contextualiza a discussão com as visões de Marx sobre o colonialismo, que via a dominação britânica na Índia como uma força “destrutiva, a outra regeneradora” contra uma sociedade estagnada, mas via o domínio na Irlanda como destrutivo e subdesenvolvedor.</li>
<li><strong>Lenin e o Imperialismo:</strong> Lenin argumentou que o imperialismo é uma fase necessária do capitalismo, impulsionada pela exportação de capital devido ao excesso de acumulação e à rivalidade entre potências capitalistas.</li>
<li><strong>O Estado Colonial:</strong> O Estado colonial não representava as classes sociais da colônia, mas subordinava-as à classe capitalista metropolitana, com a função de tornar toda a economia da colônia subserviente à economia metropolitana.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="modelos-de-sistema-mundial-frank-e-amin" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modelos-de-sistema-mundial-frank-e-amin">2. Modelos de Sistema Mundial (Frank e Amin)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tese Central:</strong> Esta perspectiva (representada por Frank e Amin) vê o desenvolvimento (ou subdesenvolvimento) do capitalismo do Terceiro Mundo como parte do desenvolvimento do processo de produção mundial.</li>
<li><strong>O Estado Dependente como Instrumento:</strong> O Estado é visto como um instrumento essencial para administrar o papel dependente dessas economias na divisão internacional do trabalho e no processo mundial de acumulação de capital.</li>
<li><strong>Natureza do Estado:</strong> O Estado periférico é “muito mais um instrumento do capital estrangeiro do que do capital local”. É relativamente forte e autônomo em relação à sua burguesia local, mas fundamentalmente fraco e dependente da burguesia internacional. Sua função é garantir o acesso aos recursos domésticos para o capital metropolitano, mobilizando fundos públicos e reformando a estrutura social para disponibilizar mão de obra para as exportações.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="dependência-histórico-estrutural-cardoso-e-faletto" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dependência-histórico-estrutural-cardoso-e-faletto">3. Dependência Histórico-Estrutural (Cardoso e Faletto)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Ênfase na Luta de Classes:</strong> Cardoso e Faletto rejeitam a derivação mecânica das sociedades dependentes unicamente da “lógica da acumulação capitalista”. Eles enfatizam a <strong>“transformação histórica das estruturas por meio de conflitos, movimentos sociais e luta de classes”</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Fatores Locais:</strong> A forma e as políticas do Estado resultam de como os “setores das classes locais se aliaram ou se chocaram com interesses estrangeiros” e organizaram diferentes formas de Estado.</li>
<li><strong>O Estado como Arena de Conflito:</strong> O Estado dependente é uma arena primária de conflito de classes, e a pressão dos grupos populares (“el pueblo”) força o Estado em uma direção democrática. O Estado é fundamental para a organização do mercado interno e da acumulação de capital local.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="o-novo-autoritarismo-autoritarismo-burocrático" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="o-novo-autoritarismo-autoritarismo-burocrático">4. O Novo Autoritarismo (Autoritarismo Burocrático)</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Características:</strong> O regime de autoritarismo burocrático é um tipo de corporatismo que é “garantidor e organizador da dominação exercida através de uma estrutura de classes subordinada às frações superiores de uma burguesia altamente oligopolizada e transnacionalizada”. Ele exclui politicamente os setores populares por meio da coerção e economicamente, redirecionando os gastos sociais para a infraestrutura e a burocracia estatal.</li>
<li><strong>Debate sobre a Origem:</strong> Enquanto Frank e O’Donnell (em sua fase inicial) argumentavam que o regime era uma resposta <strong>necessária</strong> à crise de acumulação ou à necessidade de aprofundar a industrialização, Cardoso e Stepan discordam. Eles veem o autoritarismo burocrático como uma resposta a uma <strong>exigência política</strong>—a ameaça à hegemonia da elite por movimentos populares—e o consideram um “tipo de regime político” e não uma forma estruturalmente inevitável do Estado.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="conclusão-do-capítulo" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusão-do-capítulo">Conclusão do Capítulo</h3>
<p>O capítulo conclui que o Estado autoritário é <strong>frágil</strong> devido à sua base social limitada e à “nostalgia pela democracia”. A luta pela democracia é um elemento dinâmico e unificador para a transformação social. A degeneração do autoritarismo burocrático está intimamente ligada à expansão democrática nas metrópoles.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>Text notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy1984/Carnoy1984.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hall, P. A. (1993). Policy Paradigms, Social Learning, and the State.</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Hall1993.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Hall, P. A. (1993). Policy Paradigms, Social Learning, and the State: The Case of Economic Policymaking in Britain. Comparative Politics, 25(3), 275–296. https://doi.org/10.2307/422246</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="gemini-at-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-at-google-drive"><em>Gemini at Google Drive</em></h3>
<p><strong>Política Paradigmas, Aprendizagem Social e o Estado: O Caso da Formulação de Políticas Econômicas na Grã-Bretanha</strong></p>
<p>O artigo examina a natureza da aprendizagem social e a mudança de políticas, particularmente no contexto da formulação de políticas macroeconômicas na Grã-Bretanha entre 1970 e 1989.</p>
<p><strong>Conceitos Chave:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Aprendizagem Social:</strong> Definida como uma tentativa deliberada de ajustar os objetivos ou técnicas de política em resposta à experiência passada e a novas informações.</li>
<li><strong>Paradigma de Política:</strong> Uma estrutura de ideias e padrões que especifica as metas de política, os instrumentos para alcançá-las e a natureza dos problemas a serem abordados.</li>
<li><strong>Três Tipos de Mudança de Política:</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Primeira Ordem:</strong> Mudança nos níveis (configurações) dos instrumentos de política, enquanto os objetivos e instrumentos gerais permanecem os mesmos (por exemplo, ajustes orçamentários anuais).</li>
<li><strong>Segunda Ordem:</strong> Alteração dos instrumentos de política e suas configurações, mas mantendo a hierarquia geral de objetivos (por exemplo, introdução de “limites de caixa” para gastos públicos em 1976).</li>
<li><strong>Terceira Ordem:</strong> Uma mudança radical e simultânea nas configurações de instrumentos, nos próprios instrumentos e na hierarquia de objetivos, refletindo uma “mudança de paradigma” (por exemplo, a mudança do keynesianismo para o monetarismo).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Implicações para a Teoria do Estado:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mudança de Primeira e Segunda Ordem:</strong> Corresponde bem ao modelo de aprendizagem social dos teóricos centrados no Estado, com especialistas desempenhando um papel dominante e o processo ocorrendo em grande parte dentro do próprio Estado.</li>
<li><strong>Mudança de Terceira Ordem (Mudança de Paradigma):</strong> Desvia-se do modelo centrado no Estado. Neste caso (Keynesianismo para Monetarismo):
<ul>
<li>Políticos e a mídia, em vez de funcionários públicos, desempenharam o papel preeminente.</li>
<li>O processo foi uma questão de toda a sociedade, ligada à competição eleitoral e à debate público, e não confinado aos limites do Estado.</li>
<li>O triunfo do monetarismo dependeu de competição eleitoral partidária.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Autonomia do Estado:</strong> A autonomia do Estado pode depender da presença de um paradigma de política coerente, que fornece critérios para resistir a certas pressões sociais. A desintegração do paradigma keynesiano tornou o governo mais vulnerável.</li>
<li>O artigo conclui que “poder” (luta por poder) e “quebra-cabeça” (aprendizagem social) estão frequentemente interligados na formulação de políticas públicas.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5"><em>Perplexity with Claude Sonet 4.5</em></h3>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Public Policy</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Hall1993.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hall, P. A. (2003). Aligning Ontology and Methodology in Comparative Research.</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Hall2003.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Hall, P. A. (2003). Aligning Ontology and Methodology in Comparative Research. In J. Mahoney &amp; D. Rueschemeyer (Eds.), Comparative Historical Analysis in the Social Sciences (1st ed., pp.&nbsp;373–404). Cambridge University Press. https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511803963.012</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="gemini-at-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-at-google-drive"><em>Gemini at Google Drive</em></h3>
<p><strong>Sumário do Ensaio: Alinhando Ontologia e Metodologia em Pesquisa Comparativa</strong></p>
<p>O ensaio de Peter A. Hall trata do desalinhamento entre as ontologias (pressupostos sobre a natureza das relações causais no mundo social e político) e as metodologias (meios para aumentar a confiança nas inferências, ou como gosto de dizer, teoria sobre epistemologia, teoria sobre como conhecer o mundo) predominantes na política comparada.</p>
<p><strong>Convergência Histórica de Ontologia e Metodologia:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Institucionalismo Inicial:</strong> A abordagem era descritiva e idiográfica, focada nas instituições formais, com uma ontologia circumscrita que via as instituições como produtos de histórias nacionais.</li>
<li><strong>A Revolução Comparativa (Anos 50 e 60):</strong> Houve uma mudança para a concepção do mundo político como um campo regido por regularidades causais nomológicas (leis válidas no espaço e tempo). Isso impulsionou a busca por generalizações e o desenvolvimento de taxonomias e tipologias, sendo o funcionalismo uma perspectiva causal popular.</li>
<li><strong>O Método Comparativo (Anos 60 e 70):</strong> Com a queda do funcionalismo, a ontologia mudou para imagens orientadas para variáveis, e a busca por regularidades causais passou a ser vista em termos de Mill (métodos de concordância e diferença). Lijphart definiu o método comparativo como essencialmente correlacional, análogo ao método estatístico, mas com um pequeno número de casos (pequeno-N).</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>O Dilema Contemporâneo:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>As metodologias populares (regressão padrão e método comparativo convencional) exigem fortes pressupostos ontológicos, como homogeneidade de unidade e ausência de correlação sistemática com variáveis omitidas.</li>
<li>As novas ontologias da política comparada, como as baseadas em <strong>interação estratégica</strong> e <strong>dependência de trajetória (path dependence)</strong>, violam esses pressupostos, reconhecendo a ubiquidade de:
<ul>
<li>Causação conjuntural múltipla.</li>
<li>Efeitos de interação complexos.</li>
<li>A importância da sequência e do tempo.</li>
<li>Causação recíproca.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Solução Proposta: Análise Sistemática de Processos (Systematic Process Analysis):</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>O método proposto envolve a comparação de previsões de teorias causais, não apenas sobre resultados (variável dependente) e variáveis causais (independentes), mas também sobre o <strong>processo causal</strong> em si (eventos, sequência de eventos, motivações dos atores, etc.).</li>
<li>O estudo de caso único e a pesquisa pequeno-N, quando combinados com a Análise Sistemática de Processos, tornam-se ferramentas poderosas para testar teorias, especialmente as complexas que postulam estruturas causais incompatíveis com os pressupostos da análise de regressão.</li>
<li>O objetivo final é garantir que a escolha do método seja congruente com os pressupostos ontológicos sobre as estruturas causais do mundo.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity-with-claude-sonet-4.5"><em>Perplexity with Claude Sonet 4.5</em></h3>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Methodology</category>
  <category>Epistemology</category>
  <category>Ontology</category>
  <category>Comparative Politics</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Hall2003.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Notes for EDUC-483-01-SOC-373</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-07-EDUC-483-01-SOC-373/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 







 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Class notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-07-EDUC-483-01-SOC-373/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Notes for EDUC0404</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-06-EDUC0404/2026-01-06-EDUC0404.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Positron</strong></p>
<p>What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors?</p>
<p>What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized?</p>
<p>As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong.</p>
<p>What are the interesting ideas in the paper?</p>
<p>If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you?</p>
<p>Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study?</p>
<p><em>Notes per day:</em></p>
<section id="gabriel-marconcondes-koraico-martin-carnoy-achievement-gains-and-achievement-inequality-evidence-from-brazil-2007-2017." class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gabriel-marconcondes-koraico-martin-carnoy-achievement-gains-and-achievement-inequality-evidence-from-brazil-2007-2017.">2026-01-06: Gabriel Marconcondes Koraico, Martin Carnoy: Achievement Gains and Achievement Inequality: Evidence from Brazil (2007-2017).</h2>
<p>Insights from Analysing rising test scotes and changin racial achievement gaps across school districts and States</p>
<hr>
<p>Understand better the scope and the theoretical problem</p>
<p>Understand better the methodology.</p>
<p>Brazil made substancial progress in average test scores from 2007 to 2017</p>
<p>but average gains don’t tell much abou heterogenial inequality.</p>
<p>Racial and social class are the really stron predictor of unequal oportunithi correlated with social class and rache</p>
<p>unit of analysis municipalit – saep data prova brazil 5th to 9th grades near universal coverage ofd public schools.</p>
<p>THe municipal schools and the state schools are under very differente policies under the same network</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<hr>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="perplexity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity"><em>Perplexity</em></h3>
<hr>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<hr>
<ol type="a">
<li>ideas, concepts, arguments that you found stimulating, worth remembering and building on,</li>
<li>questions, concerns, disagreements with ideas encountered,</li>
<li>connections, linkages, contradictions between one idea or approach and another.</li>
</ol>
<p>Short memos are due by 5pm Monday, the day before class. A third of your course grade will be based on the short memos. Please submit them through Canvas.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>Long memos: For four of the topics, students will prepare a more detailed memo (5 pages) assessing the weekly readings. You choose which week’s readings you wish to analyze, but you must complete this assignment before the date the topic is discussed in class. The purpose of the longer memos is to help you grapple with the readings and respond with questions, criticisms, and new ideas. The main thrust of the longer memos should be on developing promising research ideas suggested by the readings. We strongly encourage you use the long memos as a vehicle for advancing your own work. When you choose to write a longer memo about a particular topic, you should consult the additional readings for that week. Longer memos are due by 9am on Tuesdays. A third of your course grade is based on the long memos.</p></li>
<li><p>All students should arrive at class with questions, topics, and issues to be vetted and debated. You should come to class prepared to answer: What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors? What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized? As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong. What are the interesting ideas in the paper? If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you? Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study? A good seminar should have active dialog and debate. If someone proposes an idea that is contrary to your view, speak up. I will often be intentionally provocative, so be prepared to push back. Your task is to engage one another in an assessment of the readings.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Class notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-06-EDUC0404/2026-01-06-EDUC0404.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Contdid</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Callaway-etal2025-Contdid.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em></p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights’</h2>
<p>Two-Way Fixed Effects” (TWFE) é geralmente traduzido como “Efeitos Fixos Bidimensionais” ou “Efeitos Fixos de Duas Vias</p>
<p>TWFE é uma caixa reta ininteligivel,</p>
<p>Eu estou interessado no gini educacional, quero saber como as cotas impactaram nesse gini educacional</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="perplexity-using-claude-sonnet-4.5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity-using-claude-sonnet-4.5"><em>Perplexity using Claude Sonnet 4.5</em></h3>
</section>
</section>
<section id="central-research-questions-and-problems" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="central-research-questions-and-problems">Central Research Questions and Problems</h2>
<p>Carnoy examines how political power relations in capitalist democracies fundamentally shape educational systems and their distributional outcomes. The core research problem is understanding education not merely through economic frameworks, but through a political-economic lens that foregrounds how the State—reflecting unequal class, racial, and gender power structures—conditions educational opportunities and resource allocation.</p>
<p>The chapter challenges the analytical separation between political and economic power in educational analysis, arguing that wealth inequalities inherent in capitalism create quasi-class structures that crystallize within democratic State institutions, including education systems. Carnoy specifically critiques pluralist theories that disconnect political power from economic power, contending instead that long-term economic inequalities provide the most consistent explanatory framework for understanding educational policy and outcomes.</p>
</section>
<section id="core-concepts-and-theoretical-framework" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-concepts-and-theoretical-framework">Core Concepts and Theoretical Framework</h2>
<section id="the-conflictual-state" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-conflictual-state">The Conflictual State</h3>
<p>The central theoretical contribution builds on Bowles and Gintis’s framework of the tension between capitalism and democracy. Carnoy positions education as a critical site of struggle between two contradictory forces: the unequal, hierarchical market economy that generates class differentiation, and democratic promises of equal opportunity, social mobility, and human rights. This makes schooling both a reproducer of inequality (through resource disparities and class-based achievement gaps) and a potential mechanism for social transformation (through democratic struggles for inclusion and redistribution).</p>
</section>
<section id="state-generated-social-capital" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-generated-social-capital">State-Generated Social Capital</h3>
<p>Carnoy extends Coleman’s concept of social capital beyond family and community relations to theorize how States themselves can invest in social capital—through ensuring neighborhood safety, reducing school violence, or eliminating child labor—which complements human capital formation. This concept becomes particularly important when comparing educational outcomes across different political regimes, suggesting that authoritarian socialist states (Cuba, Vietnam) may generate social contexts more conducive to mass education provision than market democracies, even while capitalist societies excel at linking social capital to individual productivity.</p>
</section>
<section id="power-hierarchies-and-educational-resource-distribution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="power-hierarchies-and-educational-resource-distribution">Power Hierarchies and Educational Resource Distribution</h3>
<p>The chapter analyzes conflicts over public educational spending as manifestations of underlying power relations. Carnoy critiques Brighouse et al.’s suggestion that democratic processes constrain bureaucrats from redistributing resources from wealthy to poor families, arguing instead that bureaucrats’ decisions reflect internalized understandings of State power structures that privilege economic elites. The historical evidence from Texas school finance litigation (San Antonio v. Rodriguez) and movements for vertical equity demonstrate that democratic mechanisms—lawsuits, social movements, union organizing—actually provide the primary institutional channels through which marginalized groups challenge State bureaucracies serving wealthy interests.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="evidence-and-research-methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="evidence-and-research-methods">Evidence and Research Methods</h2>
<section id="comparative-historical-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-historical-analysis">Comparative-Historical Analysis</h3>
<p>Carnoy employs comparative-historical methods across multiple dimensions. He contrasts democratic versus authoritarian capitalist states (comparing Spain, Chile, Argentina, and Brazil under military rule with democratic periods), and capitalist versus socialist education systems (Scandinavian social democracies, East Asian developmental states, and revolutionary socialist states). This comparative framework reveals how different political-economic configurations produce varying educational outcomes and distributional patterns.</p>
</section>
<section id="legal-and-policy-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="legal-and-policy-analysis">Legal and Policy Analysis</h3>
<p>The chapter extensively analyzes U.S. Supreme Court cases (Brown v. Board of Education, San Antonio v. Rodriguez) and legal struggles over educational finance equity as empirical evidence of how class and racial power structures manifest in educational policy. These cases demonstrate the concrete mechanisms through which political conflicts over educational resources play out in capitalist democracies.</p>
</section>
<section id="engagement-with-empirical-economics-literature" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="engagement-with-empirical-economics-literature">Engagement with Empirical Economics Literature</h3>
<p>Carnoy systematically reviews econometric evidence on educational production functions, particularly the contested relationship between per-pupil spending and student achievement. He traces the evolution from Hanushek’s influential claims that spending doesn’t matter, through Friedman’s market-based voucher arguments, to more recent quasi-experimental studies using court-mandated spending increases (Jackson et al.&nbsp;2015; LaFortune et al.&nbsp;2018; Carrasco 2014 on Chile’s voucher expansion) that demonstrate large positive causal effects of increased spending on low-income student outcomes. This engagement shows how ideological positions about public sector efficiency have been adjudicated through improved empirical methods—specifically, exploiting exogenous variation in spending to identify causal effects.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="analytical-strengths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analytical-strengths">Analytical Strengths</h2>
<section id="theoretical-integration" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theoretical-integration">Theoretical Integration</h3>
<p>The chapter successfully integrates multiple theoretical traditions—neo-Marxist State theory (Gramsci, Poulantzas), institutionalism (Evans), and social capital theory (Coleman, Putnam)—into a coherent framework centered on power relations. This synthetic approach avoids reductionism while maintaining analytical clarity about how economic inequalities structure political possibilities.</p>
</section>
<section id="historical-specificity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="historical-specificity">Historical Specificity</h3>
<p>Carnoy recognizes that while power relations operate similarly across capitalist democracies, their specific manifestations depend on historical trajectories unique to each society. His discussion of Scandinavian countries’ legitimacy structures differing from Anglo-American models demonstrates sensitivity to institutional variation while maintaining the general theoretical framework.</p>
</section>
<section id="empirical-grounding-of-ideological-debates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="empirical-grounding-of-ideological-debates">Empirical Grounding of Ideological Debates</h3>
<p>The treatment of the spending effectiveness debate exemplifies rigorous empirical engagement. Carnoy acknowledges ideological preferences transparently while insisting that validity claims require empirical testing. His demonstration that improved identification strategies (using court-mandated spending changes as natural experiments) have largely resolved the spending debate in favor of effectiveness shows how methodological advances can adjudicate theoretical disputes.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="potential-weaknesses-and-critical-questions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-weaknesses-and-critical-questions">Potential Weaknesses and Critical Questions</h2>
<section id="agency-and-determinism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="agency-and-determinism">Agency and Determinism</h3>
<p>While Carnoy emphasizes that education is a site of struggle and transformation, the structural emphasis on how power hierarchies “condition” individual and group agency sometimes verges on determinism. The framework could benefit from more explicit theorization of the conditions under which subordinate groups successfully challenge power structures versus when reproduction prevails. What specific institutional features or historical conjunctures enable transformative democratic mobilization?</p>
</section>
<section id="measurement-and-operationalization" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measurement-and-operationalization">Measurement and Operationalization</h3>
<p>The concept of State-generated social capital, while theoretically valuable, lacks clear operationalization. How precisely should researchers measure cross-national variation in State-produced safety, institutional trust, or collective norms? Without clearer measurement strategies, the concept risks becoming a residual category explaining variance not captured by human capital investments.</p>
</section>
<section id="comparative-scope-conditions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-scope-conditions">Comparative Scope Conditions</h3>
<p>The comparison between authoritarian socialist and democratic capitalist educational systems raises important questions about scope conditions. Carnoy suggests socialist states excel at mass education provision due to egalitarian values and State capacity to enforce learning conditions, but the limited number of cases (Cuba, Vietnam, China pre-reform) makes generalization difficult. Additionally, the recent trajectory of China and Vietnam toward market mechanisms complicates claims about socialist versus capitalist complementarities with educational quality.</p>
</section>
<section id="causal-mechanisms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="causal-mechanisms">Causal Mechanisms</h3>
<p>While the chapter effectively demonstrates correlations between power structures and educational outcomes, the specific causal mechanisms linking class relations to policy decisions could be more precisely specified. For example, <em>how exactly</em> do wealthy elites translate economic power into educational policy influence? Through campaign finance? Social networks with bureaucrats? Ideological hegemony shaping what seems politically feasible? More micro-level analysis of decision-making processes would strengthen causal claims.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="adjudicating-disagreements" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjudicating-disagreements">Adjudicating Disagreements</h2>
<p>Several theoretical disagreements could be resolved through further empirical research:</p>
<p><strong>Democratic versus Bureaucratic Resource Allocation</strong>: Carnoy’s critique of Brighouse et al.&nbsp;suggests that authoritarian capitalist states should be <em>less</em> redistributive than democracies. This could be tested systematically by comparing educational spending progressivity across regime types, controlling for economic development—though measurement challenges around authoritarian versus democratic classification and quality of spending data would need careful attention.</p>
<p><strong>Social Capital Complementarity</strong>: The claim that socialist values complement mass education better than capitalist individualism could be examined through quasi-experimental variation in governance regimes. Natural experiments like German reunification, or cross-provincial variation in China between more market-oriented and state-controlled regions, could provide leverage on whether egalitarian institutions improve educational outcomes independent of resource levels.</p>
<p><strong>Spending Effectiveness Heterogeneity</strong>: While recent evidence supports spending effectiveness for low-income students, questions remain about whether effects vary by institutional context (decentralized versus centralized systems, strong versus weak teacher unions, high versus low State capacity). Cross-national comparative studies exploiting within-country variation in governance structures could illuminate how political-economic configurations moderate spending impacts.</p>
<p>The most interesting unresolved question is whether Carnoy’s framework predicts that <em>all</em> educational inequalities reflect power structures, or whether some inefficiencies exist that even perfectly egalitarian power distributions wouldn’t resolve. Testing this would require imagining counterfactuals where power was equalized—perhaps through analysis of maximally egalitarian cases like Cuba or Scandinavian countries—to see whether residual inequalities persist, suggesting technical rather than purely political constraints.</p>
</section>
<section id="httpsppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.comwebdirect-filesattachments1113342211a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30carnoy-2024-the-state-and-education.pdf" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="httpsppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.comwebdirect-filesattachments1113342211a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30carnoy-2024-the-state-and-education.pdf">(https://ppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.com/web/direct-files/attachments/111334221/1a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30/Carnoy-2024-The-State-and-Education.pdf)</h2>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<hr>
<section id="gemini-in-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-in-google-drive"><em>Gemini in Google Drive</em></h3>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Callaway-etal2025-Contdid.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carnoy, M. (2024). The State and Education.</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy2024Ch3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Carnoy, M. (2024). The State and Education. In The political economy of education. Cambridge University Press.</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="perplexity-using-claude-sonnet-4.5" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity-using-claude-sonnet-4.5"><em>Perplexity using Claude Sonnet 4.5</em></h3>
</section>
</section>
<section id="central-research-questions-and-problems" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="central-research-questions-and-problems">Central Research Questions and Problems</h2>
<p>Carnoy examines how political power relations in capitalist democracies fundamentally shape educational systems and their distributional outcomes. The core research problem is understanding education not merely through economic frameworks, but through a political-economic lens that foregrounds how the State—reflecting unequal class, racial, and gender power structures—conditions educational opportunities and resource allocation.</p>
<p>The chapter challenges the analytical separation between political and economic power in educational analysis, arguing that wealth inequalities inherent in capitalism create quasi-class structures that crystallize within democratic State institutions, including education systems. Carnoy specifically critiques pluralist theories that disconnect political power from economic power, contending instead that long-term economic inequalities provide the most consistent explanatory framework for understanding educational policy and outcomes.</p>
</section>
<section id="core-concepts-and-theoretical-framework" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-concepts-and-theoretical-framework">Core Concepts and Theoretical Framework</h2>
<section id="the-conflictual-state" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-conflictual-state">The Conflictual State</h3>
<p>The central theoretical contribution builds on Bowles and Gintis’s framework of the tension between capitalism and democracy. Carnoy positions education as a critical site of struggle between two contradictory forces: the unequal, hierarchical market economy that generates class differentiation, and democratic promises of equal opportunity, social mobility, and human rights. This makes schooling both a reproducer of inequality (through resource disparities and class-based achievement gaps) and a potential mechanism for social transformation (through democratic struggles for inclusion and redistribution).</p>
</section>
<section id="state-generated-social-capital" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-generated-social-capital">State-Generated Social Capital</h3>
<p>Carnoy extends Coleman’s concept of social capital beyond family and community relations to theorize how States themselves can invest in social capital—through ensuring neighborhood safety, reducing school violence, or eliminating child labor—which complements human capital formation. This concept becomes particularly important when comparing educational outcomes across different political regimes, suggesting that authoritarian socialist states (Cuba, Vietnam) may generate social contexts more conducive to mass education provision than market democracies, even while capitalist societies excel at linking social capital to individual productivity.</p>
</section>
<section id="power-hierarchies-and-educational-resource-distribution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="power-hierarchies-and-educational-resource-distribution">Power Hierarchies and Educational Resource Distribution</h3>
<p>The chapter analyzes conflicts over public educational spending as manifestations of underlying power relations. Carnoy critiques Brighouse et al.’s suggestion that democratic processes constrain bureaucrats from redistributing resources from wealthy to poor families, arguing instead that bureaucrats’ decisions reflect internalized understandings of State power structures that privilege economic elites. The historical evidence from Texas school finance litigation (San Antonio v. Rodriguez) and movements for vertical equity demonstrate that democratic mechanisms—lawsuits, social movements, union organizing—actually provide the primary institutional channels through which marginalized groups challenge State bureaucracies serving wealthy interests.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="evidence-and-research-methods" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="evidence-and-research-methods">Evidence and Research Methods</h2>
<section id="comparative-historical-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-historical-analysis">Comparative-Historical Analysis</h3>
<p>Carnoy employs comparative-historical methods across multiple dimensions. He contrasts democratic versus authoritarian capitalist states (comparing Spain, Chile, Argentina, and Brazil under military rule with democratic periods), and capitalist versus socialist education systems (Scandinavian social democracies, East Asian developmental states, and revolutionary socialist states). This comparative framework reveals how different political-economic configurations produce varying educational outcomes and distributional patterns.</p>
</section>
<section id="legal-and-policy-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="legal-and-policy-analysis">Legal and Policy Analysis</h3>
<p>The chapter extensively analyzes U.S. Supreme Court cases (Brown v. Board of Education, San Antonio v. Rodriguez) and legal struggles over educational finance equity as empirical evidence of how class and racial power structures manifest in educational policy. These cases demonstrate the concrete mechanisms through which political conflicts over educational resources play out in capitalist democracies.</p>
</section>
<section id="engagement-with-empirical-economics-literature" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="engagement-with-empirical-economics-literature">Engagement with Empirical Economics Literature</h3>
<p>Carnoy systematically reviews econometric evidence on educational production functions, particularly the contested relationship between per-pupil spending and student achievement. He traces the evolution from Hanushek’s influential claims that spending doesn’t matter, through Friedman’s market-based voucher arguments, to more recent quasi-experimental studies using court-mandated spending increases (Jackson et al.&nbsp;2015; LaFortune et al.&nbsp;2018; Carrasco 2014 on Chile’s voucher expansion) that demonstrate large positive causal effects of increased spending on low-income student outcomes. This engagement shows how ideological positions about public sector efficiency have been adjudicated through improved empirical methods—specifically, exploiting exogenous variation in spending to identify causal effects.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="analytical-strengths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analytical-strengths">Analytical Strengths</h2>
<section id="theoretical-integration" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theoretical-integration">Theoretical Integration</h3>
<p>The chapter successfully integrates multiple theoretical traditions—neo-Marxist State theory (Gramsci, Poulantzas), institutionalism (Evans), and social capital theory (Coleman, Putnam)—into a coherent framework centered on power relations. This synthetic approach avoids reductionism while maintaining analytical clarity about how economic inequalities structure political possibilities.</p>
</section>
<section id="historical-specificity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="historical-specificity">Historical Specificity</h3>
<p>Carnoy recognizes that while power relations operate similarly across capitalist democracies, their specific manifestations depend on historical trajectories unique to each society. His discussion of Scandinavian countries’ legitimacy structures differing from Anglo-American models demonstrates sensitivity to institutional variation while maintaining the general theoretical framework.</p>
</section>
<section id="empirical-grounding-of-ideological-debates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="empirical-grounding-of-ideological-debates">Empirical Grounding of Ideological Debates</h3>
<p>The treatment of the spending effectiveness debate exemplifies rigorous empirical engagement. Carnoy acknowledges ideological preferences transparently while insisting that validity claims require empirical testing. His demonstration that improved identification strategies (using court-mandated spending changes as natural experiments) have largely resolved the spending debate in favor of effectiveness shows how methodological advances can adjudicate theoretical disputes.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="potential-weaknesses-and-critical-questions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="potential-weaknesses-and-critical-questions">Potential Weaknesses and Critical Questions</h2>
<section id="agency-and-determinism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="agency-and-determinism">Agency and Determinism</h3>
<p>While Carnoy emphasizes that education is a site of struggle and transformation, the structural emphasis on how power hierarchies “condition” individual and group agency sometimes verges on determinism. The framework could benefit from more explicit theorization of the conditions under which subordinate groups successfully challenge power structures versus when reproduction prevails. What specific institutional features or historical conjunctures enable transformative democratic mobilization?</p>
</section>
<section id="measurement-and-operationalization" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measurement-and-operationalization">Measurement and Operationalization</h3>
<p>The concept of State-generated social capital, while theoretically valuable, lacks clear operationalization. How precisely should researchers measure cross-national variation in State-produced safety, institutional trust, or collective norms? Without clearer measurement strategies, the concept risks becoming a residual category explaining variance not captured by human capital investments.</p>
</section>
<section id="comparative-scope-conditions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="comparative-scope-conditions">Comparative Scope Conditions</h3>
<p>The comparison between authoritarian socialist and democratic capitalist educational systems raises important questions about scope conditions. Carnoy suggests socialist states excel at mass education provision due to egalitarian values and State capacity to enforce learning conditions, but the limited number of cases (Cuba, Vietnam, China pre-reform) makes generalization difficult. Additionally, the recent trajectory of China and Vietnam toward market mechanisms complicates claims about socialist versus capitalist complementarities with educational quality.</p>
</section>
<section id="causal-mechanisms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="causal-mechanisms">Causal Mechanisms</h3>
<p>While the chapter effectively demonstrates correlations between power structures and educational outcomes, the specific causal mechanisms linking class relations to policy decisions could be more precisely specified. For example, <em>how exactly</em> do wealthy elites translate economic power into educational policy influence? Through campaign finance? Social networks with bureaucrats? Ideological hegemony shaping what seems politically feasible? More micro-level analysis of decision-making processes would strengthen causal claims.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="adjudicating-disagreements" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adjudicating-disagreements">Adjudicating Disagreements</h2>
<p>Several theoretical disagreements could be resolved through further empirical research:</p>
<p><strong>Democratic versus Bureaucratic Resource Allocation</strong>: Carnoy’s critique of Brighouse et al.&nbsp;suggests that authoritarian capitalist states should be <em>less</em> redistributive than democracies. This could be tested systematically by comparing educational spending progressivity across regime types, controlling for economic development—though measurement challenges around authoritarian versus democratic classification and quality of spending data would need careful attention.</p>
<p><strong>Social Capital Complementarity</strong>: The claim that socialist values complement mass education better than capitalist individualism could be examined through quasi-experimental variation in governance regimes. Natural experiments like German reunification, or cross-provincial variation in China between more market-oriented and state-controlled regions, could provide leverage on whether egalitarian institutions improve educational outcomes independent of resource levels.</p>
<p><strong>Spending Effectiveness Heterogeneity</strong>: While recent evidence supports spending effectiveness for low-income students, questions remain about whether effects vary by institutional context (decentralized versus centralized systems, strong versus weak teacher unions, high versus low State capacity). Cross-national comparative studies exploiting within-country variation in governance structures could illuminate how political-economic configurations moderate spending impacts.</p>
<p>The most interesting unresolved question is whether Carnoy’s framework predicts that <em>all</em> educational inequalities reflect power structures, or whether some inefficiencies exist that even perfectly egalitarian power distributions wouldn’t resolve. Testing this would require imagining counterfactuals where power was equalized—perhaps through analysis of maximally egalitarian cases like Cuba or Scandinavian countries—to see whether residual inequalities persist, suggesting technical rather than purely political constraints.</p>
</section>
<section id="httpsppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.comwebdirect-filesattachments1113342211a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30carnoy-2024-the-state-and-education.pdf" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="httpsppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.comwebdirect-filesattachments1113342211a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30carnoy-2024-the-state-and-education.pdf">(https://ppl-ai-file-upload.s3.amazonaws.com/web/direct-files/attachments/111334221/1a391ada-4303-493c-924e-4261d4eacc30/Carnoy-2024-The-State-and-Education.pdf)</h2>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<hr>
<section id="gemini-in-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-in-google-drive"><em>Gemini in Google Drive</em></h3>
<p><strong>O Estado e a Educação: Uma Análise Político-Econômica</strong></p>
<p>Os sistemas educacionais modernos desempenham um papel econômico e social fundamental, profundamente moldado pelas relações de poder econômico e social, refletidas na estrutura política do Estado-nação.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Poder e Educação:</strong> Com a ascensão do capitalismo de mercado e da democracia política, as escolas se secularizaram e a ideologia estatal substituiu a ideologia religiosa como base para a transmissão de conhecimento e valores. As hierarquias de poder econômico/político do Estado capitalista (e pós-capitalista) substituíram a hierarquia religiosa na definição do que constitui conhecimento valioso e comportamento adequado.</li>
<li><strong>Teoria Política da Educação:</strong> As hierarquias de poder no Estado-nação secular fornecem a estrutura para uma teoria política da educação, definindo como indivíduos de diferentes classes sociais, raças, etnias e gêneros exercem agência em relação à educação e as oportunidades econômicas que enfrentam.</li>
<li><strong>Poder Desigual em Democracias Capitalistas:</strong> As grandes diferenças de renda e riqueza inerentes às economias de mercado capitalistas influenciam a força da voz individual nas decisões coletivas. O texto argumenta que essas diferenças produzem uma estrutura de classe social ou quase-classe, com características de longo prazo enraizadas no poder econômico, que o Estado reflete.</li>
<li><strong>Tensão e Conflito:</strong> O aumento concomitante do capitalismo (que é inerentemente desigual) e da democracia (que promete poder igual e mobilidade social) criou uma tensão contínua. O sistema educacional público é um local importante dessa luta entre o valor democrático da igualdade de oportunidades e as desigualdades geradas pelo capitalismo de mercado.</li>
<li><strong>Conflito por Recursos:</strong> As relações de poder no Estado são evidentes no conflito sobre como os recursos públicos são distribuídos no sistema educacional. Em sistemas financeiros públicos descentralizados, como o dos Estados Unidos, os gastos públicos médios com alunos de classes sociais mais baixas são menores do que com seus equivalentes de classes mais altas.</li>
<li><strong>Capital Social Gerado pelo Estado:</strong> O Estado pode investir em capital social (como aumentar a segurança do bairro ou reduzir a violência escolar) para influenciar a estrutura que condiciona a escolha individual. Países escandinavos, por exemplo, enfatizam a responsabilidade coletiva e a igualdade social, o que pode levar a uma educação de maior qualidade.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy2024Ch3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Template</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Text Template.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors?</p>
<p>What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized?</p>
<p>As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong.</p>
<p>What are the interesting ideas in the paper?</p>
<p>If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you?</p>
<p>Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study?</p>
<p><em>Full citation:</em></p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<hr>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="perplexity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity"><em>Perplexity</em></h3>
<hr>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<hr>
<ol type="a">
<li>ideas, concepts, arguments that you found stimulating, worth remembering and building on,</li>
<li>questions, concerns, disagreements with ideas encountered,</li>
<li>connections, linkages, contradictions between one idea or approach and another.</li>
</ol>
<p>Short memos are due by 5pm Monday, the day before class. A third of your course grade will be based on the short memos. Please submit them through Canvas.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>Long memos: For four of the topics, students will prepare a more detailed memo (5 pages) assessing the weekly readings. You choose which week’s readings you wish to analyze, but you must complete this assignment before the date the topic is discussed in class. The purpose of the longer memos is to help you grapple with the readings and respond with questions, criticisms, and new ideas. The main thrust of the longer memos should be on developing promising research ideas suggested by the readings. We strongly encourage you use the long memos as a vehicle for advancing your own work. When you choose to write a longer memo about a particular topic, you should consult the additional readings for that week. Longer memos are due by 9am on Tuesdays. A third of your course grade is based on the long memos.</p></li>
<li><p>All students should arrive at class with questions, topics, and issues to be vetted and debated. You should come to class prepared to answer: What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors? What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized? As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong. What are the interesting ideas in the paper? If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you? Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study? A good seminar should have active dialog and debate. If someone proposes an idea that is contrary to your view, speak up. I will often be intentionally provocative, so be prepared to push back. Your task is to engage one another in an assessment of the readings.</p></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Text Template.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Do, or not to do? That’s the question</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Reading Notes</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>State Theory</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Carnoy, M. (1989). Education, State, and Culture in American Society.</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy1989/Carnoy1989.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Carnoy, M. (1989). Education, State, and Culture in American Society. In H. A. Giroux &amp; M. Carnoy (Eds.), Critical pedagogy, the state, and cultural struggle. State University of New York Press.</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
<p>O texto de Martin Carnoy avança no debate paradigmário, ou na discussão sobre ontologias educacionias, talvez seja um dos primeiros textos a ressaltar isso tão fortemtente, conforme faz Paulo Freire também. Talvez uma das principais virtudes de Carnoy é ter se misturado tão fortemtente com tantas tradições diferentes de politica educacional, possibilitanto o desenvolvimento dessa perspectiva.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
<p>O texto de Martin Carnoy analisa o sistema educacional dos Estados Unidos como um espaço de conflito político e cultural entre a ideologia dominante das classes empresariais e as aspirações de grupos subordinados. O autor explora como o Estado utiliza as escolas para promover a legitimação política e o desenvolvimento econômico, tentando integrar imigrantes e minorias em uma cultura nacional que favoreça a produtividade capitalista. Contudo, essa dinâmica não é unilateral, pois os movimentos sociais pressionam as instituições por maior igualdade e currículos inclusivos, transformando a educação em uma arena de resistência e negociação constante. Em última análise, a obra busca demonstrar que o ensino público serve tanto para a reprodução da estrutura de classes quanto como um campo fértil para a emergência de contra-hegemonias que desafiam o status quo.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<p>A tese central apresentada por Martin Carnoy no ensaio <em>“Education, State, and Culture in American Society”</em> é a de que o sistema educacional americano (e o Estado em geral) não é meramente um instrumento monolítico da classe dominante para reproduzir desigualdades, nem uma instituição puramente democrática de mobilidade social. Em vez disso, a educação é definida como um <strong>campo de conflito e contradição</strong> moldado pela luta contínua entre duas forças opostas: as forças “reprodutivas” do capital e as forças “democratizantes” dos movimentos sociais.</p>
<p>Aqui estão os pontos principais que sustentam essa tese no texto:</p>
<p><strong>1. O Estado como Arena de Luta (Dualidade de Fins)</strong> Carnoy rejeita a visão simplista de que as escolas apenas impõem uma ideologia dominante ou que servem apenas para a mobilidade social. Ele argumenta que o Estado capitalista democrático tem objetivos contraditórios:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Reprodução:</strong> Precisa socializar a mão de obra para a produção capitalista, o que gera desigualdades, hierarquias e injustiças naturais ao sistema econômico.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Democratização:</strong> Precisa promover o ideal de um Estado democrático, respondendo às demandas por igualdade e mobilidade social para manter sua legitimidade política,. Consequentemente, a educação americana é o produto histórico tanto das tentativas da classe dominante de moldar a escola para suas necessidades quanto das tentativas dos grupos subordinados de expandir e democratizar o acesso.</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>2. Cultura Dominante vs.&nbsp;Ideologia</strong> A tese distingue entre “cultura” (a totalidade de padrões de comportamento e a capacidade de fazer história de uma comunidade) e “ideologia” (uma versão a-histórica da cultura imposta pelo grupo dominante). * O grupo dominante tenta impor sua “ideologia de negócios” (individualismo, consumo, meritocracia) como se fosse a cultura nacional. * No entanto, para manter a hegemonia, a cultura dominante precisa ceder e incorporar elementos das culturas subordinadas, tornando-se mais “popular” para garantir o consenso. Assim, as vitórias dos movimentos sociais (como direitos civis) alteram a própria natureza da cultura dominante, embora a elite empresarial tente constantemente reabsorver essas mudanças para manter o controle.</p>
<p><strong>3. A Natureza da Resistência e a Contra-hegemonia</strong> Carnoy argumenta contra a ideia de que o fracasso escolar ou a rejeição da escola sejam formas eficazes de resistência política. * <strong>Resistência Falsa:</strong> Quando estudantes marginalizados rejeitam a escola (“acting out”) ou abandonam os estudos, isso é frequentemente uma reação pessoal que acaba reforçando sua posição subordinada, pois lhes nega o acesso ao conhecimento necessário para o poder político. * <strong>Contra-hegemonia Real:</strong> A verdadeira resistência exige que os grupos subordinados permaneçam na escola e exijam acesso ao “conhecimento dominante” (habilidades intelectuais, ciência, matemática), não para aceitar a ideologia empresarial, mas para usar essas ferramentas na luta política democrática.</p>
<p><strong>4. O Papel da Educação na Mudança Social</strong> A conclusão da tese é que as escolas são locais onde o conflito social mais amplo (baseado em raça, gênero e classe) é disputado. O sucesso dos movimentos sociais não está em criar enclaves culturais separados, mas em travar uma “guerra de posição” (usando o termo gramsciano citado no texto) dentro das instituições públicas para redefinir o conhecimento e a cultura nacional.</p>
<p>Em suma, a educação é descrita não como um mecanismo estático de controle, mas como um <strong>processo dialético</strong> onde a hegemonia é constantemente desafiada e renegociada através da ação política dos grupos subordinados dentro de um Estado democrático contraditório.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="gemini-in-google-drive" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gemini-in-google-drive"><em>Gemini in Google Drive</em></h3>
<p><strong>Educação, Estado e Cultura na Sociedade Americana (Resumo)</strong></p>
<p>O ensaio de Martin Carnoy analisa o papel das escolas públicas americanas na <strong>incorporação de ondas heterogêneas de imigração a uma “cultura” nacional de massa</strong> e a relação complexa entre educação, estado e cultura em uma sociedade capitalista democrática.</p>
<p><strong>Interpretações da Reforma Escolar:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Uma interpretação sugere que as escolas impõem uma ideologia dominante para socializar imigrantes e a “gentalha” da classe baixa em uma força de trabalho disciplinada.</li>
<li>Outra interpretação argumenta que as escolas incorporam estudantes em um conjunto de normas e valores que já refletem a cultura de massa, sendo a aceitação o mínimo para evitar a alienação.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>O Estado Capitalista Democrático e a Educação:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>O estado capitalista democrático tem objetivos educacionais contraditórios:
<ul>
<li>Um papel <strong>“reprodutivo”</strong>: socializar e treinar a força de trabalho e fazer as desigualdades do capitalismo parecerem naturais, impondo uma representação ideológica da cultura empresarial dominante.</li>
<li>Um papel <strong>“democratizante”</strong>: incutir ideais democráticos e responder às demandas por acesso igualitário a bens e serviços.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>A educação americana é o produto de forças <strong>reprodutivas</strong> (tentativas da classe dominante de impor sua visão) e forças <strong>democratizantes</strong> (tentativas de grupos subordinados de moldar as escolas para o desenvolvimento de suas culturas).</li>
<li>As escolas públicas são um alvo principal do conflito social entre o capital e o trabalho e os movimentos sociais que buscam maior igualdade.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cultura e Ideologia:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cultura</strong> é a “totalidade de padrões de comportamento socialmente transmitidos, artes, crenças, instituições e todos os outros produtos do trabalho e pensamento humano característicos de uma comunidade ou população”.</li>
<li><strong>Ideologia</strong> é uma versão ahistórica da cultura da classe dominante. É a concepção do grupo dominante sobre o que o grupo subordinado deve aspirar. A aceitação da ideologia dominante implica a separação da cultura de grupo anterior, mas em uma democracia, a participação política individual permite influenciar a mudança cultural.</li>
<li>A resistência, em contraste com a “saída” apolítica, é o conflito com a escola por parte de estudantes que entendem a visão da escola como uma barreira ao desenvolvimento cultural de seu grupo. O sucesso escolar para estudantes marginalizados significa inclusão, incorporação e expansão da cultura de massa.</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Reading notes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Carnoy1989/Carnoy1989.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The State and Industrial Transformation: Insights from Peter Evans () Embedded Autonomy: States and Industrial Transformation</title>
  <dc:creator>Tales Mançano</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Evans1995.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>Full citation:</em> Evans, P. B. (1995). Embedded autonomy: States and industrial transformation. Princeton University Press.</p>
<hr>
<p>What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors?</p>
<p>What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized?</p>
<p>As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong.</p>
<p>What are the interesting ideas in the paper?</p>
<p>If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you?</p>
<p>Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study?</p>
<section id="personal-notes-and-highlights" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-notes-and-highlights">Personal Notes and highlights</h2>
<p>Uma coisa que me marcou nesse livro é a metafora inicial dos leões que comem burocratas, me parece uma otima metáfora, mas não é assim que começaria o livro.</p>
<p>As Evans puts it: “Identification with the escaped lion is natural, but until less hierarchical ways of avoiding a Hobbesian world are discovered, the state lies at the center of solutions to the problem of order. Without the state, markets, the other master institution of modern society, cannot function. We do not spend our valuable time standing in lines in front of the counters of bureaucrats because we are masochists. We stand there because we need what the state provides. We need predictable rules, and these in turn must have a concrete organizational structure behind them. Fervent calls for the dismantling of the state by late-twentieth-century capitalist free-marketeers served to derail the state’s ability to act as an instrument of distributive justice, but not to reduce its overall importance.”</p>
<p>How this text makes me feel:</p>
<p>Eu não soumuito fã desse estudo de livro, é meio confuso para mim, As metáforas são legais, mas a forma como constroi o problema teórico, bem, não é tanto a minha praia. Fico pensando nas confounders e em perder o ponto, é um modelo de livro bastante aberto, me da um pouco de frio na Barriga.</p>
<p>— Central questions (Mix Me and LLM)</p>
<p>What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors?</p>
<p>Evans central problem is how state structures and state-society relations shape possibilities for <strong>industrial transformation</strong> in newly industrializing countries (NICs). The core puzzle is: why do some states successfully promote economic development while others impede it? More specifically, he asks whether states can deliberately change their position in the international division of labor, especially in technologically demanding sectors like information technology. Theoretically, his contribution is a shift from debating “how much” states intervene to what kind” of state involvement matters, and <strong>why</strong> states differs in those perspectives. He challenges the neo-utilitarian (or liberal) orthodoxy dominant in the 1980s that portrayed state intervention as inevitably creating rent-seeking behavior and economic distortions.</p>
<p>Derivative questions (in portuguese):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Não “quanto” o Estado deve intervir, mas “que tipo” de intervenção e estrutura estatal promove o desenvolvimento?.</li>
<li>Por que alguns estados (como a Coreia do Sul) conseguem promover a transformação industrial e outros (como o Zaire) se tornam predadores que destroem a economia?.</li>
<li>Como as estruturas internas do Estado e suas relações com a sociedade (especificamente a classe industrial) variam e impactam o desenvolvimento?.</li>
<li>É possível para países de industrialização tardia (NICs) alterarem deliberadamente sua posição na divisão internacional do trabalho, construindo vantagens comparativas em setores de alta tecnologia (como a informática)?</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Core Concepts</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Embedded Autonomy:</li>
</ol>
<p>The book’s central theoretical concept is “embedded autonomy”—an apparently contradictory combination of bureaucratic insulation and deep social ties. Evans argues that developmental states require both: - 1.1 Autonomy: Weberian bureaucratic coherence through meritocratic recruitment, long-term career rewards, and corporate identity that prevents individual incumbents from pursuing purely personal goals</p>
<ul>
<li><p>1.2 Embeddedness: Dense concrete ties binding the state to society through institutionalized channels for continual negotiation of goals and policies</p></li>
<li><p>1.3 Neither element works alone. Pure autonomy would lack intelligence and implementation capacity, while embeddedness without internal coherence would prevent the state from transcending individual private interests.</p></li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>State Roles</li>
</ol>
<p>Evans develops four analytical categories to describe state involvement patterns:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Custodian</strong>: Regulatory role privileging policing over promotion, aimed at preventing or restricting private initiatives</li>
<li><strong>Demiurge</strong>: Direct state production assuming private capital incapable of sustaining necessary commodity production</li>
<li><strong>Midwifery</strong>: Assisting emergence of new entrepreneurial groups through protection, subsidies, and signaling</li>
<li><strong>Husbandry</strong>: Ongoing support for established firms facing global challenges through R&amp;D support and complementary state activities</li>
</ul>
<p>Evans argues midwifery-husbandry combinations work better than custodian-demiurge approaches.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Evidence and Research Methods</strong></p>
<p>Evans employs a <strong>comparative institutional approach</strong> combining multiple evidence types:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Case Selection</strong> He examines three NICs—Brazil, India, and Korea that were chosen because they represent countries desperate enough to attempt transformation but less constrained than raw material exporters (?). Within each, he focuses on the information technology sector during the 1970s-1980s as an exceptionally strong test case.</p></li>
<li><p>Data Sources</p></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Secondary literature</strong>: Scholarly accounts and World Bank analyses</li>
<li><strong>Government documents and statistics</strong>: Regulatory agency data, industry association publications</li>
<li><strong>Key informant interviews</strong>: Dozens of current and former government officials and private executives provided crucial insights into state structures, bureaucratic dynamics, and firm strategies</li>
<li><strong>Business press</strong>: Day-to-day reporting on firm and product evolution</li>
<li><strong>Firm-level data</strong>: Annual reports and corporate publications</li>
</ul>
<p>Evans emphasizes avoiding state reification by examining specific agencies, organizations, and individual actors. He acknowledges that informants offer biased accounts, but treats these biases as evidence themselves, juxtaposing theories from different bureaucratic positions.</p>
<p><strong>Strengths of the Analysis</strong></p>
<p><strong>Theoretical Innovation</strong></p>
<p>Evans successfully moves beyond sterile debates about market versus state by demonstrating that <strong>variation in state structures matters more than degree of intervention</strong>. His embedded autonomy concept elegantly synthesizes Weber’s bureaucratic theory, Gerschenkron’s developmental state insights, and contemporary analysis of East Asian success.</p>
<p>The framework effectively explains why Korea outperformed Brazil and India: Korea approximated embedded autonomy while the others exhibited “partial and imperfect approximations”. His sectoral analysis validated these general patterns—Korea’s Ministry of Communications-ETRI-chaebol networks epitomized embedded autonomy, while India’s Department of Electronics showed the costs of insufficient embeddedness.</p>
<p><strong>Empirical Richness</strong></p>
<p>Evans provides compelling evidence that <strong>developing countries can construct comparative advantage in high-technology sectors</strong>, contradicting conventional economic wisdom. By the late 1980s, Korea had become one of the world’s largest semiconductor producers, Brazil had created a multibillion-dollar locally-owned computer industry, and India developed significant software export capacity.</p>
<p>His analysis reveals surprising patterns: comparative advantage lay not in low-wage assembly but in <strong>skilled intellectual labor and design-intensive production</strong>. India excelled in software engineering despite negative value-added in routine assembly. Brazil achieved international competitiveness in financial automation systems.</p>
<p><strong>Dynamic Analysis</strong></p>
<p>Perhaps most impressive is Evans’s attention to how <strong>successful transformation changes the political foundations of state involvement</strong>. He documents a contradictory dynamic: nationalist greenhouse (<em>Protectionism</em>) policies created local entrepreneurial groups that eventually allied with transnational corporations, undercutting political support for the very state agencies that helped create them.</p>
<p>This insight contradicts neo-utilitarian predictions of static rent-seeking symbiosis between officials and firms. Instead, Evans finds that “state involvement was associated with economic dynamism, and the result was political contestation, not symbiosis”.</p>
</section>
<section id="weaknesses-and-limitations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="weaknesses-and-limitations">Weaknesses and Limitations</h2>
<section id="incomplete-political-dynamics-theory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="incomplete-political-dynamics-theory">Incomplete Political Dynamics Theory</h3>
<p>Evans acknowledges a “serious lacuna” in his framework. While the comparative institutional approach facilitated uncovering contradictory political dynamics, <strong>it did not predict them</strong>. His initial discussion offered ideas about how states affect transformation but “had relatively little to say about how this transformation would change the basis of subsequent state involvement”.</p>
<p>The book documents how successful midwifery produces “gravediggers” that undermine developmental state coalitions, but doesn’t provide a systematic theory of this process. When do transformative projects strengthen versus undermine their own foundations?</p>
</section>
<section id="measurement-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="measurement-challenges">Measurement Challenges</h3>
<p>Evans’s concepts, while analytically powerful, face <strong>operationalization difficulties</strong>. How precisely do we measure “embeddedness”? When does a state cross from “partial approximation” to genuine embedded autonomy? The framework sometimes appears post-hoc—we know Korea succeeded, therefore it must have had embedded autonomy.</p>
<p>The reliance on interview data, while providing rich texture, raises questions about <strong>selection bias and generalizability</strong>. How representative were Evans’s informants? Did survivorship bias shape which officials and entrepreneurs he interviewed?</p>
</section>
<section id="sectoral-specificity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sectoral-specificity">Sectoral Specificity</h3>
<p>The information technology focus provides analytical leverage but raises questions about <strong>external validity</strong>. IT is characterized by rapid technological change, relatively low capital intensity compared to steel or chemicals, and possibilities for modular production. Do Evans’s findings apply to other sectors with different characteristics?</p>
<p>He acknowledges this concern but argues IT provides an “exceptionally strong test” precisely because conventional wisdom would predict state involvement should fail. Still, the scope conditions of embedded autonomy remain underspecified.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="interesting-and-provocative-ideas" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interesting-and-provocative-ideas">Interesting and Provocative Ideas</h2>
<section id="bureaucracy-as-scarce-resource" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bureaucracy-as-scarce-resource">Bureaucracy as Scarce Resource</h3>
<p>Evans inverts conventional wisdom: <strong>“It is the scarcity of bureaucracy that undermines development, not its prevalence”</strong>. While bureaucracy remains pejorative for citizens and policymakers, Evans shows that approximating Weberian bureaucratic ideals is exceptionally difficult in most Third World states, and its absence cripples developmental efforts.</p>
</section>
<section id="user-producer-linkages" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="user-producer-linkages">User-Producer Linkages</h3>
<p>The analysis of Brazil’s financial automation sector reveals how <strong>tight user-producer linkages can generate international competitiveness despite high component costs</strong>. When major banks were simultaneously producers and users, intimate knowledge of local idiosyncrasies translated into custom-designed systems that were 30% cheaper than international alternatives.</p>
</section>
<section id="learning-state-agencies" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-state-agencies">Learning State Agencies</h3>
<p>Evans documents remarkable institutional evolution: India’s Department of Electronics, initially dedicated to protecting state-owned ECIL, transformed itself toward promotion rather than policing. Despite neo-utilitarian predictions that bureaucrats would defend their regulatory power, DOE officials embraced liberalization because they were “immersed in a project of transformation that was of greater interest than minor individual perquisites”.</p>
<p>This suggests that <strong>technocratic commitment to sectoral success can override bureaucratic self-interest</strong>—a finding with profound implications for institutional reform.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="points-of-disagreement-and-evidence-requirements" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="points-of-disagreement-and-evidence-requirements">Points of Disagreement and Evidence Requirements</h2>
<section id="the-inevitability-of-internationalization" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-inevitability-of-internationalization">The Inevitability of Internationalization</h3>
<p>Evans argues the “new internationalization” of the late 1980s—growing alliances between local firms and TNCs—was “in part the product of successful midwifery” rather than simply “the empire strikes back”. This interpretation seems optimistic. <strong>What evidence would distinguish successful developmental partnerships from recolonization?</strong></p>
<p>To be persuasive, we would need: - Longitudinal data on <strong>value capture</strong>: Do local firms in joint ventures retain growing shares of profits, or do returns accrue primarily to TNC partners? - <strong>Technology transfer metrics</strong>: Are local capabilities deepening, or are firms becoming dependent on proprietary TNC technology? - <strong>Trajectory analysis</strong>: Do alliance firms eventually compete independently, or do they devolve into permanent subsidiaries?</p>
<p>Evans provides some evidence on these questions but acknowledges “the specter of getting trapped in the high-tech equivalent of trading cheap cotton for expensive cloth remained real”. More systematic comparison of alliance outcomes versus autonomous development paths would strengthen the argument.</p>
</section>
<section id="state-capacity-thresholds" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-capacity-thresholds">State Capacity Thresholds</h3>
<p>Evans argues that even Brazil and India, with “partial and imperfect approximations” of embedded autonomy, achieved significant results. But <strong>how much state capacity is minimally necessary?</strong> What happens in cases below Brazil and India’s level?</p>
<p>To adjudicate this, we would need: - Analysis of <strong>failed cases</strong>: Countries that attempted similar policies but achieved worse outcomes - <strong>Threshold identification</strong>: Specific capacity indicators (meritocratic recruitment rates, bureaucratic tenure patterns, institutionalized state-business consultation mechanisms) that distinguish effective from ineffective states - <strong>Decomposition studies</strong>: Which elements of embedded autonomy are necessary versus sufficient?</p>
</section>
<section id="counterfactual-scenarios" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="counterfactual-scenarios">Counterfactual Scenarios</h3>
<p>Evans’s strongest claim is that state involvement <strong>caused</strong> industrial transformation. But <strong>what would have happened without these policies?</strong> Korea’s chaebol were already powerful before specific IT policies. Would they have entered the sector anyway?</p>
<p>Persuasive evidence would include: - <strong>Within-country variation</strong>: Comparing sectors with and without state support in the same country - <strong>Timing analysis</strong>: Demonstrating that firm entry followed rather than preceded policy changes - <strong>Firm-level studies</strong>: Showing that state support influenced specific investment decisions</p>
<p>Evans provides some such evidence (e.g., the timing of Korean chaebol entry into semiconductors following state initiatives) but systematic analysis remains limited.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="empirical-adjudication-possibilities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="empirical-adjudication-possibilities">Empirical Adjudication Possibilities</h2>
<p>Many of Evans’s arguments <strong>can be adjudicated through further empirical study</strong>:</p>
<section id="state-structure-measurements" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-structure-measurements">State Structure Measurements</h3>
<p>Comparative surveys could measure Weberian characteristics across countries: recruitment procedures, career patterns, salary structures, professionalization indicators. Correlating these with developmental outcomes would test the embedded autonomy hypothesis more rigorously.</p>
</section>
<section id="network-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="network-analysis">Network Analysis</h3>
<p>Contemporary social network analysis tools could map state-business ties, measuring embeddedness density, reciprocity, and centralization. Comparing network structures across successful and unsuccessful cases would validate or challenge Evans’s framework.</p>
</section>
<section id="long-term-performance-tracking" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="long-term-performance-tracking">Long-term Performance Tracking</h3>
<p>Following the IT sectors Evans studied into the 21st century reveals whether his predictions held. Did Korean firms move up the value chain? Did Brazilian and Indian alliances lead to capability deepening or hollowing out? Such longitudinal analysis tests the theory’s predictive power.</p>
</section>
<section id="mechanisms-testing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mechanisms-testing">Mechanisms Testing</h3>
<p>Evans proposes specific mechanisms (e.g., midwifery induces entrepreneurial entry, husbandry sustains competitiveness). Case studies examining variation in these mechanisms and their effects would identify which are essential and under what conditions.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Evans provides a theoretically sophisticated and empirically rich analysis that fundamentally advances our understanding of state roles in industrial transformation. His embedded autonomy concept elegantly captures the paradoxical requirements of developmental states, while his sectoral analysis demonstrates that even technologically demanding industries are amenable to strategic state action.</p>
<p>The book’s greatest contribution may be its dynamic perspective: recognizing that successful transformation reshapes the political foundations of future state action. This insight opens crucial questions about the sustainability of developmental coalitions and the reconstruction of state-society relations—questions that remain central to development studies today.</p>
<hr>
<section id="countries-classification" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="countries-classification">Countries Classification</h3>
<p>Com base na obra <em>Embedded Autonomy</em> de Peter Evans, a classificação dos países nos conceitos de estrutura estatal, bem como a justificativa para a escolha dos estudos de caso, pode ser detalhada da seguinte forma:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Classificação dos Países e Conceitos Evans utiliza três categorias principais para classificar os estados com base em suas estruturas internas (burocracia) e suas relações externas com a sociedade (inserção):</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Estado Predatório (Exemplo: Zaire sob Mobutu):</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Características:</strong> Falta de burocracia competente e ausência de regras previsíveis. Os cargos públicos são tratados como propriedade privada para extração de riqueza pessoal, onde “tudo está à venda”. O Estado atua contra o desenvolvimento, extraindo excedentes da sociedade sem fornecer bens coletivos em troca.</li>
<li><strong>Justificativa:</strong> O Zaire (atual República Democrática do Congo) é usado como o arquétipo do “pesadelo neoutilitário”, onde a lógica de mercado domina o comportamento administrativo sem qualquer coerência corporativa.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Estado Desenvolvimentista (Exemplos: Japão, Coreia do Sul, Taiwan):</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Características:</strong> Possuem <strong>Autonomia Inserida</strong> (<em>Embedded Autonomy</em>). Combinam uma burocracia weberiana meritocrática e coesa (autonomia) com redes densas de conexão com o setor industrial privado (inserção).</li>
<li><strong>Justificativa:</strong> O Japão é o modelo original, mas a Coreia do Sul é o foco principal da análise empírica de Evans. O Estado coreano conseguiu disciplinar e apoiar os grandes conglomerados (<em>chaebol</em>) para promover a transformação industrial e exportações.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Estado Intermediário (Exemplos: Brasil e Índia):</strong>
<ul>
<li><strong>Características:</strong> Exibem aproximações parciais da autonomia inserida. Não são puramente predatórios, mas carecem da coerência total dos estados desenvolvimentistas.
<ul>
<li><strong>Brasil:</strong> Caracterizado por uma burocracia fragmentada, modernizada por “adição” e não por transformação, resultando em “bolsões de eficiência” (como o BNDE) cercados por clientelismo. As relações com a sociedade são muitas vezes individualizadas (“anéis burocráticos”) em vez de institucionais.</li>
<li><strong>Índia:</strong> Possui uma longa tradição burocrática (o IAS), mas sofre de uma inserção ineficaz. O Estado manteve-se historicamente isolado e ambivalente em relação ao capital privado, focando em regulação restritiva (o “raj de licenças”) em vez de promoção conjunta.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li>Por que esses países foram escolhidos? Peter Evans selecionou explicitamente o <strong>Brasil, a Índia e a Coreia do Sul</strong> como o trio central para sua análise comparativa. As razões para essa escolha são:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Novos Países Industrializados (NICs):</strong> A escolha focou em países em desenvolvimento que fossem grandes ou avançados o suficiente para suportar uma gama completa de produção industrial. Eles representam o grupo para o qual o desafio da transformação industrial é mais saliente.</li>
<li><strong>Diversidade de Abordagens:</strong> À primeira vista, é um trio improvável, o que enriquece a comparação:
<ul>
<li>O <strong>Brasil</strong> era o arquétipo do “desenvolvimento dependente”, impulsionado por multinacionais e desigualdade social.</li>
<li>A <strong>Índia</strong> era conhecida por sua tendência à autarquia e desconfiança do capital privado.</li>
<li>A <strong>Coreia do Sul</strong> era o modelo de crescimento liderado por exportações e grandes conglomerados locais.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Fator Comum (Envolvimento Estatal):</strong> Apesar das diferenças, em todos os três casos, o envolvimento do Estado na industrialização é inegável. Isso permitiu a Evans testar sua tese de que a questão não é “quanto” o Estado intervém, mas “como”.</li>
</ul>
<ol start="3" type="1">
<li>Qual a justificativa para o foco no setor de Informática? Evans escolheu analisar a indústria de <strong>Tecnologia da Informação (TI)</strong> nesses três países como uma lente para testar suas teorias por razões estratégicas:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>O Teste Difícil:</strong> A indústria de informática é um setor de alta tecnologia e rápida mudança, onde a sabedoria convencional (neoliberal) diria que o Estado tem menos chances de sucesso e deveria intervir menos. Se o Estado pode desempenhar um papel transformador aqui, o argumento a favor da intervenção estatal é fortalecido.</li>
<li><strong>Conspiração Multidimensional:</strong> A TI é vista como o setor com maior probabilidade de gerar externalidades positivas e impulsionar o desenvolvimento no final do século XX.</li>
<li><strong>Controlar Variáveis:</strong> Ao olhar para o mesmo setor em três países diferentes, Evans pôde controlar as características tecnológicas e de mercado, focando nas variações causadas pelas diferentes estruturas estatais e papéis adotados (Custodiante, Demiurgo, Parteira, Husbandry).</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="llm-generated-content" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="llm-generated-content">LLM Generated content</h2>
<hr>
<section id="notebooklm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notebooklm"><em>NotebookLM</em></h3>
</section>
<section id="perplexity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="perplexity"><em>Perplexity</em></h3>
<hr>
<p><em>NotebookLM</em> : #### <em>Qual a tese central do texto?</em></p>
<hr>
<ol type="a">
<li>ideas, concepts, arguments that you found stimulating, worth remembering and building on,</li>
<li>questions, concerns, disagreements with ideas encountered,</li>
<li>connections, linkages, contradictions between one idea or approach and another.</li>
</ol>
<p>Short memos are due by 5pm Monday, the day before class. A third of your course grade will be based on the short memos. Please submit them through Canvas.</p>
<ol start="2" type="1">
<li><p>Long memos: For four of the topics, students will prepare a more detailed memo (5 pages) assessing the weekly readings. You choose which week’s readings you wish to analyze, but you must complete this assignment before the date the topic is discussed in class. The purpose of the longer memos is to help you grapple with the readings and respond with questions, criticisms, and new ideas. The main thrust of the longer memos should be on developing promising research ideas suggested by the readings. We strongly encourage you use the long memos as a vehicle for advancing your own work. When you choose to write a longer memo about a particular topic, you should consult the additional readings for that week. Longer memos are due by 9am on Tuesdays. A third of your course grade is based on the long memos.</p></li>
<li><p>All students should arrive at class with questions, topics, and issues to be vetted and debated. You should come to class prepared to answer: What are the central research questions or problems raised by the authors? What core concepts, evidence, and research methods are utilized? As you do the readings, think about what the author did right as well as wrong. What are the interesting ideas in the paper? If you disagree with an argument, what would it require to persuade you? Can these differences be adjudicated through further empirical study? A good seminar should have active dialog and debate. If someone proposes an idea that is contrary to your view, speak up. I will often be intentionally provocative, so be prepared to push back. Your task is to engage one another in an assessment of the readings.</p></li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="note" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="note">Note</h2>
<p>This post was first written as a reading exercise for the course <a href="../2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/"><strong>EDUC 306B</strong></a>, this was my second reading of the text.</p>
</section>
<section id="overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>In <strong>EDUC 306B: Global Education Policy &amp; Organization</strong> we recently delved into the work of <strong>Peter Evans</strong>, specifically his 1995 most famous book, **.</p>
<p>Evans provides a critical framework for understanding why some states succeed at industrialization while others fail, focusing on the internal structure of the state and its relationship with society.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="what-is-embedded-autonomy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-embedded-autonomy">🏗️ What is “Embedded Autonomy”?</h2>
<p>The central thesis of the book is that the state’s ability to transform its economy depends on a unique structural combination:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Autonomy (Corporate Coherence):</strong> A professional, meritocratic bureaucracy that can act independently of narrow interest groups.</li>
<li><strong>Embeddedness (Social Ties):</strong> A dense network of connections to the private sector that allows the state to gather information and implement policy.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The state must be sufficiently autonomous to avoid being captured, but sufficiently embedded to be effective.”</p>
</blockquote>
<section id="state-archetypes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-archetypes">State Archetypes</h3>
<p>Evans contrasts different types of states based on their developmental outcomes:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">State Type</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Characteristics</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Examples</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Developmental</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">High Embedded Autonomy; fosters growth.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">South Korea</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Intermediate</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Mixed capacity; inconsistent results.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Brazil, India</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Predatory</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Lacks autonomy; extracts wealth from society.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Zaire (DRC)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-four-roles-of-the-state" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-four-roles-of-the-state">🛠️ The Four Roles of the State</h2>
<p>Evans identifies how states engage with the industrial sector, particularly in high-tech fields like informatics during the 1970s and 80s:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Custodian:</strong> The regulator. Focuses on “policing” and setting legal frameworks.</li>
<li><strong>Demiurge:</strong> The producer. The state acts as a player by creating State-Owned Enterprises (SOEs).</li>
<li><strong>Midwifery:</strong> The promoter. Fostering the birth of new private sector firms through protection or incentives.</li>
<li><strong>Husbandry:</strong> The nurturer. Supporting existing firms to help them navigate global competition and R&amp;D.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="case-studies-brazil-india-and-korea" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="case-studies-brazil-india-and-korea">🌎 Case Studies: Brazil, India, and Korea</h2>
<p>Evans uses an <strong>institutional comparative approach</strong> to analyze the IT and computer industries. He argues that:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>South Korea</strong> succeeded through a combination of <em>Midwifery</em> and <em>Husbandry</em>, moving quickly into global markets.</li>
<li><strong>Brazil and India</strong> initially focused on the <em>Demiurge</em> and <em>Custodian</em> roles, which provided mixed results in the high-tech sector.</li>
</ul>
<p>The lesson for us in <strong>EDUC 306B</strong> is clear: industrial and educational outcomes are not just about “good policy”—they depend on the <strong>character of the state structures</strong> that implement them.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="personal-reflection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-reflection">💡 Personal Reflection</h2>
<p>Reading Evans helps bridge the gap between “politics” and “economics.” It suggests that for educational reforms to be successful, the state must not only have the <em>will</em> to change but also the <em>institutional capacity</em> and <em>social connections</em> to see that change through.</p>
</section>
<section id="chapter-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chapter-3">Chapter 3</h2>
<hr>
<p><strong>References</strong> Evans, P. B. (1995). <em>Embedded Autonomy: States and Industrial Transformation</em>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</p>
<hr>
<section id="next-steps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3>
<p><strong>Would you like me to help you draft a specific section comparing the “Husbandry” role in Brazil versus South Korea based on Evans’ analysis?</strong></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Reading Notes</category>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>State Theory</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/Evans1995.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>About the EDUC-306B</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="description" class="level1">
<h1>Description</h1>
<p><em>EDUC 306B</em>: Global Education Policy &amp; Organization. “The Politics of Education Policy”</p>
<p><em>Proposed Course Objectives</em>: The objectives of this course are (1) to introduce students to the nature of some current major debates in educational reforms from a political economy point of view; (2) to give students a grasp of various conceptions of the State—of the workings of the “political system” and the political structures in society; and, through this understanding, (3) to be able better to conduct policy analyses of education, interpret the meaning of existing educational structures and of educational reforms and gain insights into theories of educational change. Although most educational policy is developed within the context of the national State, in the past fifty years there have been important—and some say, increasing—political influences on national States from international organizations. We will also analyze literature on globalization and global governance and try to come to some conclusions about the importance of those influences. By the end of the course, everyone should have a clear idea of how to analyze education policy through a political economy approach and with an explicit theory of the state.</p>
</section>
<section id="first-impressions-2026-01-01" class="level1">
<h1>First Impressions (2026-01-01)</h1>
<p>O cusrso est’’a organiado em 18 seções que mesclam teorias mais abstratas sobre o Estado com discussões bastante aplicadas sobre políticas específicas, a disciplina alterna questões teóricas com estudos de caso.</p>
<p>O curso começa com uma aula introdutoria sobre porque estado importa, vai para as teorias liberais e do mecano, depois cobre o debate entre institucionalistas e gramscianos,,pluralistas, raça, gênero, socialismo etc. Uma pergunta a ser feita para o Carnoy é “How many theories of State are there? What does a theory have to be to be considered a theory of the State?”</p>
<p>Carnoy faz muito bme o que podemos chamar de debate paradigmático da educação, educação não é nem só um investimento tal qual um investimento em capital produtivol, nem simplesmente uma forma de dominação e doutrinação das classes dominantes, nem apenas um instrumento redistributivo e de libertação, depede de qual educação se fala e embora um ou outro modelo educacional possa ser pretominante em determinado país reguão ou momento histórco ou a educação destinada a grupos específicos, geralmente vemos diversidades de educac’~ao e resuktadis</p>
<p>Class titles:</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li><p>Session 1, Week 1, Monday, January 5: <strong>Why Does the State Matter in Educational Policy Analysis?</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 2, Week 1, Wednesday, January 7: <strong>Case Study 1: Educational Privatization in the Low-income Countries</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 3, Week 2, Monday, January 12: <strong>Theories of the State: Dependency Theory and Embedded Autonomy</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 4, Week 2, Wednesday, January 14: <strong>Case Study 2: Educational Privatization in Middle-and High-income Countries</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Monday, January 12: <strong>Martin Luther King Day</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 5, Week 3, Wednesday, January 21: <strong>Theories of the State: Liberal Common Good Theories and Markets</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 6, Week 4, Monday, January 26: <strong>Case Study 3: Public Sector Accountability Reforms (including Standards Reforms)</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 7, Week 4, Wednesday, January 28: <strong>Theories of the State: The Institutionalists versus the Gramscians</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 8, Week 5, Monday, February 2: <strong>Case Study 4: Vocational Education in Europe and Brazil</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 9, Week 5, Wednesday, February 4: <strong>Theories of the State: Educational Borrowing and Education and Legitimacy</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 10, Week 6, Monday, February 9: <strong>Case Study 5: Persistent Achievement Gaps across Race, Class, and Gender</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 11, Week 6, Wednesday, February 11: <strong>Theories of the State: Pluralists, Class Conflict, and Social Reproduction</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 12, Week 7, Wednesday, February 18: <strong>Theories of the State: The Racial State and Racial Capitalism</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 13, Week 8, Monday, February 23: <strong>Theories of the State: Gender and the State</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 14, Week 8, Wednesday, February 25: <strong>Case Study 6: PISA, TIMSS, and the Global Institutions</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 15, Week 9, Monday, March 2: <strong>Theories of the State: Globalization and the Decline of the Nation State?</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 16, Week 9, Wednesday, March 4: <strong>Case Study 7: Education in Transition in Cuba and China</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 17, Week 10, Monday, March 9: <strong>Theories of the State: Socialist States and States in Transition</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Session 18, Week 10, Wednesday, March 11: <strong>Course Wrap-up, Q&amp;A, Discussion of Final Paper</strong></p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Classes Notes:</p>
<section id="session-1-why-does-the-state-matter-in-educational-policy-analysis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="session-1-why-does-the-state-matter-in-educational-policy-analysis">Session 1: Why Does the State Matter in Educational Policy Analysis?</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><a href="../../posts/Carnoy1989/Carnoy1989.html">Carnoy1989</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="../../posts/Carnoy2024Ch3.html">Carnoy2024-Ch3-Political-Economy-Education</a></p></li>
</ul>
<section id="section" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="section"></h4>
<p>It’s hard to disagree with such broad statement, he basically says, well</p>
<p>we can make it more standardized</p>
<p>private section is important for public education - private companies can compete with each other for creating the best textbooks</p>
<p>WHo is goint to compare and to those compariosons? The economists, right</p>
<p>Who came up with the commoc core? the governmente</p>
<p>Federal money is only 9% of the education budget, states get all the power from the thing.</p>
<p>Higher stantarde</p>
<p>state public sector reform in massachusets - introduces competition in the private sector, he doesnt understande textbook markets, only written for larger states.</p>
<p>He doesnt now how the markets work anyway - khan academy, what is he talking about</p>
<p>Selling idea - what is he theoyof the state? he akonwledge that the state that decides, but then he comes back adn pay for capitalism, when the educational system has very little to do with capitalism</p>
<p>why are we buying the texteb bookd</p>
<p>you are going to get a bad score.</p>
<p>that is not neoliberalism, sking the state to step in, merging difrent hings, why does he feels the need to merge that. Federela government and the associations</p>
<p>individual state regulatory capture is not good for competiotion</p>
<p>THEACHER TRAINING:::: that’s why common core was not adopted - that was the main problem, the teachers institutions - Massive teacher training – thestes scores, the doesn’t mention the training of theachers</p>
<p>california suspendede the test for three years before they could do that.</p>
<p>QUestion of money to train all those teachers to make sure that they cna implement this corriculum.</p>
<p>Gates he is biased in the power of government.</p>
<p>Why is he the one sharing thoughts in common core?</p>
<p>He cares about it, he will profit about it? Why is he?</p>
<p>Gates: state mathers – opublic sector matthers - theories of state that matters - various theories of state – the state, part of state, politics, can have autonomy - the state can have aitonomy from politics,</p>
<p>make everything better for the system</p>
<p>the main problem is not the fact that he nevers mentions that you have to fund all of this, is that it’s basically a thecnical problem, just introduce the best tecnology and solve diference – in educatio he belives in off the shelves solutions also, and that is also a problem of the state that says that it’s tecnical and never finantioal, he never mentions any of these.</p>
<p>state theories that says that all those theories are ideological, never allow theories core values.</p>
<p>any political debates knoledge we should know as a society, what is missing for the socierty.</p>
<p>education system is inehently politisl s pst of the sttate the political sustem becauso both in democratic and outhoritaion free market ans inven in state</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="social-mobility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="social-mobility">social mobility</h2>
<p>Conforme discutido em <a href="../2025-01-01-Evans1995-Embedded-Autonomy/">Carnoy1989</a></p>
<hr>
<p>Colonial Legacies in pakistan world bank, teacher don’t show uo, cheap private schools should solve the probem, makert solution at a low fee. TEACHER ABSENTEISM</p>
<p>OIST COL</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Syllabus</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>Classes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>draft</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Mechanisms-in-SSciences/draft.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Mecanismos nas ciencias sociais, algumas tipologias de mecanismso ficaram muito famosas nas ciencias sociais, publicar algumas tpologias as vezes leva a grande sucesso editorial, existem tipologias de mecanismos (Drift, Conversion,</p>
<p>Mimetic, Coercitive, Legal Isomorphism</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Ideas</category>
  <category>Concepcts</category>
  <category>Core Ideas</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Mechanisms-in-SSciences/draft.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
