<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Tales Mançano</title>
<link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Tales Mançano Academic Website</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Do, or not to do? That’s the question</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Reading Notes</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>State Theory</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Deciding-Classes-Stanford/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The State and Industrial Transformation: Insights from Peter Evans</title>
  <dc:creator>Tales Mançano</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2025-01-01-Evans1995-Embedded-Autonomy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="note" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="note">Note</h2>
<p>This post was first written as a reading exercise for the course <a href="../2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/"><strong>EDUC 306B</strong></a>, this was my second reading of the text.</p>
</section>
<section id="overview" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview">Overview</h2>
<p>In our discussions for <strong>EDUC 306B: Global Education Policy &amp; Organization</strong>, we recently delved into the work of <strong>Peter Evans</strong>, specifically his 1995 most famous book, <em>Embedded Autonomy: States and Industrial Transformation</em>.</p>
<p>Evans provides a critical framework for understanding why some states succeed at industrialization while others fail, focusing on the internal structure of the state and its relationship with society.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="what-is-embedded-autonomy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-embedded-autonomy">🏗️ What is “Embedded Autonomy”?</h2>
<p>The central thesis of the book is that the state’s ability to transform its economy depends on a unique structural combination:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Autonomy (Corporate Coherence):</strong> A professional, meritocratic bureaucracy that can act independently of narrow interest groups.</li>
<li><strong>Embeddedness (Social Ties):</strong> A dense network of connections to the private sector that allows the state to gather information and implement policy.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The state must be sufficiently autonomous to avoid being captured, but sufficiently embedded to be effective.”</p>
</blockquote>
<section id="state-archetypes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="state-archetypes">State Archetypes</h3>
<p>Evans contrasts different types of states based on their developmental outcomes:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
<col style="width: 33%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">State Type</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Characteristics</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Examples</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Developmental</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">High Embedded Autonomy; fosters growth.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">South Korea</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Intermediate</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Mixed capacity; inconsistent results.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Brazil, India</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;"><strong>Predatory</strong></td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Lacks autonomy; extracts wealth from society.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">Zaire (DRC)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-four-roles-of-the-state" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-four-roles-of-the-state">🛠️ The Four Roles of the State</h2>
<p>Evans identifies how states engage with the industrial sector, particularly in high-tech fields like informatics during the 1970s and 80s:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Custodian:</strong> The regulator. Focuses on “policing” and setting legal frameworks.</li>
<li><strong>Demiurge:</strong> The producer. The state acts as a player by creating State-Owned Enterprises (SOEs).</li>
<li><strong>Midwifery:</strong> The promoter. Fostering the birth of new private sector firms through protection or incentives.</li>
<li><strong>Husbandry:</strong> The nurturer. Supporting existing firms to help them navigate global competition and R&amp;D.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="case-studies-brazil-india-and-korea" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="case-studies-brazil-india-and-korea">🌎 Case Studies: Brazil, India, and Korea</h2>
<p>Evans uses an <strong>institutional comparative approach</strong> to analyze the IT and computer industries. He argues that:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>South Korea</strong> succeeded through a combination of <em>Midwifery</em> and <em>Husbandry</em>, moving quickly into global markets.</li>
<li><strong>Brazil and India</strong> initially focused on the <em>Demiurge</em> and <em>Custodian</em> roles, which provided mixed results in the high-tech sector.</li>
</ul>
<p>The lesson for us in <strong>EDUC 306B</strong> is clear: industrial and educational outcomes are not just about “good policy”—they depend on the <strong>character of the state structures</strong> that implement them.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="personal-reflection" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-reflection">💡 Personal Reflection</h2>
<p>Reading Evans helps bridge the gap between “politics” and “economics.” It suggests that for educational reforms to be successful, the state must not only have the <em>will</em> to change but also the <em>institutional capacity</em> and <em>social connections</em> to see that change through.</p>
</section>
<section id="chapter-3" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chapter-3">Chapter 3</h2>
<hr>
<p><strong>References</strong> Evans, P. B. (1995). <em>Embedded Autonomy: States and Industrial Transformation</em>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</p>
<hr>
<section id="next-steps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3>
<p><strong>Would you like me to help you draft a specific section comparing the “Husbandry” role in Brazil versus South Korea based on Evans’ analysis?</strong></p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Reading Notes</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>State Theory</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2025-01-01-Evans1995-Embedded-Autonomy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2026-01-02-Carnoy2014-Ch3-Political-Economy-Education</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-Carnoy2024-Ch3-Political-Economy-Education/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>O Estado e a Educação: Uma Perspectiva Político-Econômica</p>
<p>Os sistemas educacionais modernos desempenham um papel econômico e social fundamental, profundamente moldado pelas relações de poder econômico e social refletidas no Estado-nação. Poder e Estrutura do Estado: Escolas e instituições de ensino superior são majoritariamente públicas e, portanto, produtos de forças político-econômicas. O texto argumenta que as diferenças inerentes de renda e riqueza nas economias de mercado capitalistas criam uma estrutura de classe social ou quase-classe que influencia as desigualdades de poder. Essa estrutura de poder desigual na democracia capitalista, onde a riqueza se traduz em poder político, fornece a estrutura para uma teoria política da educação. Apesar da influência do poder econômico de uma minoria, a democracia é a principal instituição através da qual a maioria pode pressionar por políticas redistributivas, como o aumento de impostos sobre os ricos para financiar escolas com menos recursos. Conflito e Legitimidade: O sistema educacional é um local central de conflito entre a desigualdade do mercado e a promessa democrática de mobilidade social e direitos humanos, incluindo igualdade de oportunidades. O sistema educacional busca reproduzir as desigualdades de renda e riqueza, mas também é um local de luta por direitos e oportunidades. A educação serve como uma fonte de legitimidade para o Estado ao tentar gerenciar o conflito entre a democracia e as relações de poder desiguais da economia de mercado. Conflito por Recursos: As relações de poder são claras no conflito sobre como os recursos públicos são distribuídos no sistema educacional. O gasto público em alunos de classes sociais mais baixas, especialmente em sistemas financeiros descentralizados, tende a ser menor do que em seus equivalentes de classes sociais mais altas. Um debate político e ideológico questiona se o aumento do gasto público melhora o desempenho dos alunos. Estudos mais recentes sugerem que o aumento do gasto por aluno tem um impacto positivo significativo nos resultados educacionais para distritos escolares de baixa renda. Capital Social Gerado pelo Estado: O Estado pode investir em capital social (como segurança e redução da exploração do trabalho infantil) para complementar o capital humano, influenciando o sucesso acadêmico, especialmente para crianças de classes sociais mais baixas. Os estados socialistas autoritários, por exemplo, foram mais bem-sucedidos do que os capitalistas na entrega de educação de massa de alta qualidade devido ao maior investimento e ao capital social socialista (ênfase na igualdade, segurança e alto valor na educação).</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Reading Notes</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>State Theory</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-Carnoy2024-Ch3-Political-Economy-Education/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>About the EDUC-306B</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="description" class="level1">
<h1>Description</h1>
<p><em>EDUC 306B</em>: Global Education Policy &amp; Organization. “The Politics of Education Policy”</p>
<p><em>Proposed Course Objectives</em>: The objectives of this course are (1) to introduce students to the nature of some current major debates in educational reforms from a political economy point of view; (2) to give students a grasp of various conceptions of the State—of the workings of the “political system” and the political structures in society; and, through this understanding, (3) to be able better to conduct policy analyses of education, interpret the meaning of existing educational structures and of educational reforms and gain insights into theories of educational change. Although most educational policy is developed within the context of the national State, in the past fifty years there have been important—and some say, increasing—political influences on national States from international organizations. We will also analyze literature on globalization and global governance and try to come to some conclusions about the importance of those influences. By the end of the course, everyone should have a clear idea of how to analyze education policy through a political economy approach and with an explicit theory of the state.</p>
</section>
<section id="first-impressions-2026-01-01" class="level1">
<h1>First Impressions (2026-01-01)</h1>
<p>O cusrso est’’a organiado em 18 seções que mesclam teorias mais abstratas sobre o Estado com discussões bastante aplicadas sobre políticas específicas, a disciplina alterna questões teóricas com estudos de caso.</p>
<p>O curso começa com uma aula introdutoria sobre porque estado importa, vai para as teorias liberais e do mecano, depois cobre o debate entre institucionalistas e gramscianos,,pluralistas, raça, gênero, socialismo etc. Uma pergunta a ser feita para o Carnoy é “How many theories of State are there? What does a theory have to be to be considered a theory of the State?”</p>
<p>Carnoy faz muito bme o que podemos chamar de debate paradigmático da educação, educação não é nem só um investimento tal qual um investimento em capital produtivol, nem simplesmente uma forma de dominação e doutrinação das classes dominantes, nem apenas um instrumento redistributivo e de libertação, depede de qual educação se fala e embora um ou outro modelo educacional possa ser pretominante em determinado país reguão ou momento histórco ou a educação destinada a grupos específicos, geralmente vemos diversidades de educac’~ao e resuktadis</p>
<p>Class titles:</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li>Session 1, Week 1, Monday, January 5: <strong>Why Does the State Matter in Educational Policy Analysis?</strong></li>
<li>Session 2, Week 1, Wednesday, January 7: <strong>Case Study 1: Educational Privatization in the Low-income Countries</strong></li>
<li>Session 3, Week 2, Monday, January 12: <strong>Theories of the State: Dependency Theory and Embedded Autonomy</strong></li>
<li>Session 4, Week 2, Wednesday, January 14: <strong>Case Study 2: Educational Privatization in Middle-and High-income Countries</strong></li>
<li>Session 5, Week 3, Wednesday, January 21: <strong>Theories of the State: Liberal Common Good Theories and Markets</strong></li>
<li>Session 6, Week 4, Monday, January 26: <strong>Case Study 3: Public Sector Accountability Reforms (including Standards Reforms)</strong></li>
<li>Session 7, Week 4, Wednesday, January 28: <strong>Theories of the State: The Institutionalists versus the Gramscians</strong></li>
<li>Session 8, Week 5, Monday, February 2: <strong>Case Study 4: Vocational Education in Europe and Brazil</strong></li>
<li>Session 9, Week 5, Wednesday, February 4: <strong>Theories of the State: Educational Borrowing and Education and Legitimacy</strong></li>
<li>Session 10, Week 6, Monday, February 9: <strong>Case Study 5: Persistent Achievement Gaps across Race, Class, and Gender</strong></li>
<li>Session 11, Week 6, Wednesday, February 11: <strong>Theories of the State: Pluralists, Class Conflict, and Social Reproduction</strong></li>
<li>Session 12, Week 7, Wednesday, February 18: <strong>Theories of the State: The Racial State and Racial Capitalism</strong></li>
<li>Session 13, Week 8, Monday, February 23: <strong>Theories of the State: Gender and the State</strong></li>
<li>Session 14, Week 8, Wednesday, February 25: <strong>Case Study 6: PISA, TIMSS, and the Global Institutions</strong></li>
<li>Session 15, Week 9, Monday, March 2: <strong>Theories of the State: Globalization and the Decline of the Nation State?</strong></li>
<li>Session 16, Week 9, Wednesday, March 4: <strong>Case Study 7: Education in Transition in Cuba and China</strong></li>
<li>Session 17, Week 10, Monday, March 9: <strong>Theories of the State: Socialist States and States in Transition</strong></li>
<li>Session 18, Week 10, Wednesday, March 11: <strong>Course Wrap-up, Q&amp;A, Discussion of Final Paper</strong></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Conforme discutido em <a href="../2025-01-01-Evans1995-Embedded-Autonomy/">no post sobre Embedded Autonomy</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Courses</category>
  <category>Syllabus</category>
  <category>Political Economy</category>
  <category>Classes</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-02-EDUC-306B/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>draft</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Mechanisms-in-SSciences/draft.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Mecanismos nas ciencias sociais, algumas tipologias de mecanismso ficaram muito famosas nas ciencias sociais, publicar algumas tpologias as vezes leva a grande sucesso editorial, existem tipologias de mecanismos (Drift, Conversion,</p>
<p>Mimetic, Coercitive, Legal Isomorphism</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Ideas</category>
  <category>Concepcts</category>
  <category>Core Ideas</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/posts/2026-01-03-Mechanisms-in-SSciences/draft.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 08:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Quarto Academic Website Examples and Tips</title>
  <link>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/</link>
  <description>Examples and tips for Quarto Academic Website</description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://drganghe.github.io/quarto-academic-website-template/files/images/placeholder1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
